Gandhiji was a tremendous man. One has to learn a lot from him.
गांधीजी एक जबरदस्त इंसान थे। उनसे बहुत कुछ सीखना होगा।
He was not at all a hypocrite, that's one thing and he was not like modern, we say,
एक बात है, कि वह बिल्कुल भी पाखंडी नहीं थे, और हम कहें, कि वह आधुनिक
politicians, who say something do something - no - he was very outspoken
राजनेताओं की तरह भी नहीं थे जो कहते कुछ हैं और करते कुछ और - नहीं - वह बहुत स्पष्टवादी या मुखर थे
and always he put himself on the testing point and he used to confess, if he made
और हमेशा उन्होंने खुद को परीक्षण बिंदु पर डाला और वह फ़ौरन कबूल करते, अगर उनसे
mistakes, immediately. One very great incident, I remember when I was a small child,
कोई गलती हो जाये। एक बहुत ही महान घटना, मुझे याद है। जब मैं छोटी बच्ची थी,
they were having a meeting together and we girls were there only sitting,
वह लोग एक साथ मिलकर बैठक कर रहे थे और हम लड़कियाँ वहाँ केवल बैठी थीं,
giving them water and things to all the people, all the big people were there like
उन लोगों को पानी और सब कुछ देने के लिए - सभी बड़े लोग वहाँ थे, जैसे
Jawaharlal Nehru was there and also Maulana Azad, all these people were sitting there.
जवाहरलाल नेहरू वहाँ थे और मौलाना आजाद भी थे, ये सब लोग वहीं बैठे थे।
They were discussing something and then suddenly, Mahatmaji said that,
वह लोग कुछ चर्चा कर रहे थे और फिर अचानक महात्मा जी ने कहा कि,
"Now it's very late, we'll have lunch here," so, they said, "Yes, yes we'll have lunch here."
"अब बहुत देर हो चुकी है, हम यहाँ दोपहर का भोजन करेंगे," तो, उन लोगों ने कहा, "हाँ, हाँ हम यहाँ दोपहर का भोजन करेंगे।"
They had to go to the guest house, which was far away. So, Mahatmaji asked for the
उन लोगों को गेस्ट हाउस जाना था, जो कि दूर था। तो महात्मा जी ने
Bai's, his wife - she had gone out - so, he got up. He had a key with him, you see,
बाई, अपनी पत्नी के लिए पूछा - वह बाहर गयीं हुईं थीं - तो, वह उठे। आप देखिए, उनके पास एक चाबी
always of this store room. He opened the store room and he asked the people,
हमेशा भंडार कक्ष की रहती थी। उन्होंने भंडार कक्ष खोला और उन लोगों को,
who were in charge of cooking, to measure everything according to the people there are,
जो कि खाना पकाने के प्रभारी थे, कहा, कि वहाँ मौजूद लोगों के अनुसार
properly everything, you see and then when they measured it out, everything was done
सब कुछ ठीक से माप लें। और फिर जब उन लोगों ने नाप लिया, सब कुछ हो गया
then he put the key back and then he went and sat there nicely. So, these people said,
फिर उन्होंने चाबी वापस रख ली और फिर चले गए और वहाँ अच्छे से बैठ गए। तो, इन लोगों ने कहा,
"Bapu, we did not know you had to take so much trouble, you see, to go all the way
"बापू, हम नहीं जानते थे कि आपको इतनी परेशानी उठानी पड़ेगी, आप देखें, कि इतनी दूर जाकर
and measure out everything for us." He didn't take much time (about) fifteen minutes,
और हमारे लिये सब कुछ नाप कर निकालें।" उन्हें ज्यादा समय नहीं लगा (लगभग) पंद्रह मिनट,
but still, so he said, "What do you think? This is the blood of my country, I cannot
लेकिन फिर भी, तो उन्होंने कहा, "तुम्हें क्या लगता है? यह मेरे देश का खून है, मैं
allow it to be wasted." See, that's the sign of a person, who understands the value of
इसे बर्बाद नहीं होने दे सकता।" देखिए, यह चिन्ह है उस व्यक्ति का, जो कि मूल्य समझता है
public money - that's just ingrained in him but those who saw him, also felt
जनता के पैसे का - वह बस उनमें अन्तर्निहित था, लेकिन जिन्होंने भी उन्हें देखा, उन्होंने भी महसूस किया
that, "Look at this man, who's living like a ascetic, absolutely, in the sense that
कि, "देखो इस व्यक्ति को , जो बिल्कुल एक तपस्वी की तरह जी रहा है, इस मायने में कि,
he would not touch the public money and that is one of the keys for all the leaders,
वह जनता के पैसे को नहीं छुएंगे और यह सभी नेताओं के लिए एक कुंजी है,
if they are absolutely above the money, then only people will respect, otherwise
यदि वे पैसों से बिल्कुल ऊपर हैं, तभी लोग उनका सम्मान करेंगे, वरना
there's no way out. But, if you find these days in every country, so much of
और कोई रास्ता नहीं है। लेकिन, आजकल आप ये पाते हैं कि हर देश में इतना
corruption, hypocrisy, then you are really shocked.
भ्रष्टाचार, पाखंड है, कि आप वास्तव में हैरान हैं।